[Music]
no I don't mind the enemy at all I think
I want an enemy I want an interlocutor I
want somebody who says something
different from me and also Wesley thank
Plato and Rousseau and count all right
very well meaning they're very seductive
yeah
meaning they're hard guys to fight okay
that's good but I got Nietzsche with me
and I got haggled with me and I got
probably her starting with me too I dare
say so so I you know I got a lot of
thinkers who are with me I just studied
different topics they did essentially
you know I'm not that different from the
nurse that matter either the guy who
speaks the truth he's probably gonna be
attacked by the people who are in and
it's gonna be portrayed as if he's out
meaning he's probably right I'm
Scandinavian and I deal well with the
drones and we guts cuz we're Germanic
peoples he comes from Northern Europe
and we throw things at each other and we
like fucking Vikings and we throw it all
out we use harsh words and the next day
we say yeah I was a bit overdoing it
yesterday on he's all kept to the
digital memory it's all there I'm not
gonna deny that I did it it's just part
of my personal history live with it okay
that's Canon Aidan and what I find
problematic with English is that even
when they're right they're still
obsessed in tonality in education
England produce theatre and drama and
everything in director brilliant death
the brilliant you were the brilliant
good side are the bridge and I think
when it comes direct communication
English find that incredibly hard to do
and that's why you don't have a rich
floor you know Pantheon on English
Philosopher's you have you David you and
yeah you have maybe white did and the
rest you know Berkeley and Smith's and
all that they're pretty embarrassing
today he says like no I'm sorry but
philosophy was taken on by the French
and the Germans and we're doing an
attempt in Scandinavia to catch up with
them you know we're not reading English
philosophers and scan today we're
reading the Germans of the French they
speak forward they they're not covering
it up they they go straight to the point
because they did point out what's
important they don't get a walk around
and try to be popular anything like that
I mean
for also he tries to be popular is
definitely media that's why nobody reads
Sean Passat on you know why would you
mm-hmm
no he was leading the barricades in
Paris in 1967 the reason why he was
popular he was leading the barricade
simply because he eat there was nothing
there there wasn't anything there the
higher they didn't do better no we don't
care that's not true any longer
there's a reason he's not that he's in
or out it was a too much of a fad right
yeah he didn't get right down into the
exactly exactly what you read no G
survived he was the only french
extension east you still interesting
today yes yep you can go back to mop
what do you starting again again again
you can't do the resort can come he he
became a novelist it's just like the
other guys were too interested in being
popular in the streets of Paris they
were not interesting doom profound work
that without Lester and the philosopher
doesn't care if he's understood while
he's alive first calling you do your
philosophy is like maybe I'll say
something profound one day yeah and then
one idea was brilliant and he will then
be part of the history of philosophy
yeah it's very hard to have one idea
isn't it I mean that's the best in the
world to actually create one idea Wow
I mean the men are modernist guys
haven't done that I mean they no no no
no couldn't pace they've cut and paste a
bunch of ideas together like a Buell
Airy but we're cooler than you are no
you know the other guy they were putting
down was too young like oh those unions
and those Peter Sohn Ian's and
well young young young had some ideas
for certainly he wasn't a philosopher
but I think you and I doing it wisely
and I think Brendan O'Neill in England
gets it I think would you and I'm
Brendan have in common is that we all
agree that Jordan Peterson something
very important to say and we're very
grateful that he's around and let him do
that first and let him have his for this
is the year we go critical about John
Peterson you only go critical about what
people project on him not what he says
mmm-hmm the guy is nerving pretentious
he's not pretending anything is not he
hasn't claimed to be the king the people
making he's just pretended to be the
priest that he is crazy to Jordan I
proudly swatter the projection on Jordan
Peterson he's gonna give you the answer
and what you must do in your life come
forward he will not do that and he can't
do that you can't ask Canadian Prairie
and nerd for that he doesn't have the
background to be able to say that so
your generation he opens up he opens up
the door yeah yes yeah we prefer a prety
provides a masculine figure in the
culture which is has none I mean there's
almost none right I mean there's a lot
of men but very few of them cry in
public for example or even shout or have
it you know I don't know how to say that
but there's so many talking heads out
there that are that are so on in human
in some sense they're just they've just
become a language or they become a they
all take advice from communication
agencies yeah they communicate but they
don't spiel
don't never ever I mean we should close
down advertising completely and ban it
outright so you know before it has to
kill itself anyway advertising is over
marketing is oh yeah it's you obsession
with image when you just train you to
not be yourself to train you to be
theatrical they train you to always
cover your ass because communication
agency employees yeah trying to cover
their ass at all time and then send you
bill
no those are the worst mentors or
advisers you can ever have yeah worst
ever they will take away the one thing
you should keep which is your own
personality yeah especially in the
digital environment and because Jordan
came from out of nowhere and it was
never given advice by communication you
see when he sat in front of the cameras
and the microphones and started talking
he thought yes he's real yeah exactly
it's like seeing somebody real it's like
oh wow somebody real there's there's so
much unreality out there it's like he
doesn't matter even to me almost almost
on some level it doesn't even matter to
me well you know he's the content of
what he's saying is very important
as well but but but but his own
fantasies authenticity is as much a part
of that the whole thing as as the
content authenticity was right maybe all
about authenticity and then about
quality so ok you see me authenticity
comes first and then quality comes after
so it's not special effects it's people
want to yea we're not listening unless
somebody's authentic the one they are
authentic and they have something
meaningful to say then adds to our
knowledge we will listen more mm-hmm
then you retract this is not the age of
revolutions this is not digital selfies
to revolution mean they're not gonna be
real loose industry everything you do
industries on yellow vests or occupy
whether we do fails it fails cause it's
just surrealism it's just it's just data
some it won't take you anywhere it
becomes damp t-shirt and a slogan three
weeks later it's over
that's not a way do you think sir I
didn't really track what do you mean by
a retraction what do you mean by that
can you explain I'm an quickly he's the
philosopher who wrote a book called the
faith of faithless that inspired us to
write since as much in credits its final
radio Samak which is a British
philosopher British working class based
in New York brilliant thinker okay what
Simon said that he's an anarchist he
came from the left and he said everybody
out there wants the revolution
romanticizing Paris 1967 you know they
romanticize in Paris 1789 no no that's
gonna happen in our time and if it
happens gonna be over in three weeks and
become a t-shirt and an Instagram
picture nothing else because people are
prepared they don't have staying power
they don't have sustainability they
don't take the long-term view they don't
know what they're doing
meaning ok don't know what you're doing
the only thing to do is to realize we
live in an age of chaos and the only way
to understand the chaos and bring order
decay is to retract meaning you move to
the countryside you build a monastery
with your best friends you connect that
monastery to the Wi-Fi you connected
with the rest the world we also isolate
yourself you concentrate your thinking
you made it take contemplate study study
study and then at the drawing board you
start seeing pattern
that other people don't see suddenly
you're getting connected with the other
people who see what you see because
they've done the same thing you discover
the people create monasteries in North
America Europe Asia Australia they will
get connected this movement to people
who just step back loose their ego
completely it fascinated with the world
and realize that the only feeling of
values today is to bring order into
chaos that takes hard work to understand
how complex the world is and understand
the patterns in this complexity yeah
then find possible solutions okay that
takes retraction that's what it's called
because when you say no we've got to
leave society and move out in the forest
and create sustainable monasteries only
able foundation left in society are
gonna be the monastery yeah
everything else will fail well I've been
meditating for years I mean I think
traction isn't it I mean that's
retraction meditation that's like well
the difference between a guy who comes
to the door has bipolarity diagnosis 23
years old you know perfectly well under
the first thing it is that we've gotta
try to get you off the medication and
see if you can find something else the
works better for you how about your
meditation started their focus every
morning don't have 15 things in your
head decide one thing you do do that one
thing that's it when it goes the next
yeah sure no meditation is absolutely
necessary we cannot concentrate and
decide what's important to us unless we
do that the other version of doing that
is when you work in the team is the
drawing board it's incredibly important
to me I do all my lectures with white
boards and boards I don't ever do
PowerPoint I hate fucking PowerPoint
it's just so bad no no I do the board
I draw when I give lectures I do the
same thing with the guys that work with
velocities believe it or not done on
drawing boards it's about proportions
it's about priorities
it's about hurricane and it's about
creating different playing fields for
example after the printing press in 1450
you get a certain playing field is being
developed through the indictment in
Europe in the seventeen hundreds and you
get a mouth and the guys have got the
map like Napoleon
became the winners this mark Napoleon
those guys got the map right if you get
the map Hegel's map in this case you get
the game ok new era did its will arise
in the nineteen eighties changes
everything blows up everything and
digitalize us it
everything has to become digital or else
it dies and if that flattens the the
sort of pyramidical structure of a
Napoleon world world
in our first book the net across that we
wrote 20 years ago would say history has
to be understood as different fields of
imminence its adolescent term the fields
of innocence there's a certain field
there's a certain plan it's a certain
Mac you could talk to Jordan Hall and
Dennis Mac doing these guys in the
states of friends of ours they haven't
probably studied the list you still talk
about games there's a model of a cabin
of a saint Cindy
certain things that make this game
necessary to be played in a certain way
the certain rules yet up to follow you
gotta be powerful and mass media society
you'd better own or control mass media
you better own and control education
academic institutions you better own and
control capital because that's the
resource that's the blood of the whole
system you better own and control the
city because that's where everything's
gonna take place that's where you're
gonna build the factory on which you
build your fortune and your power and
you've got to build a nation-state
around that city because you need to
plunder the countryside for the
workforce for labor and for resources
that's how the work that's how the
nation-state was because otherwise
somebody did the research to the cities
you now in the sense we're moving away
from the nation-state it's completely
right it's dead it's not about
exploitation resource any longer it's
about use reuse it's a resource of
meaning you can go vertical instead of
horizontal you don't even need to sit in
that case he changes everything the
world physics uses everything your
countries on the planet today called
Singapore Hong Kong and Dubai they don't
even have territory why
taras just expensive it's just
transportation it's fossil fuel huh
vertical so Berlin because we strive
towards the digital so the digital is
changing everything and technologies to
go with that for example like air
conditioning which may places like
Singapore habitable and and you know and
also in Canada in Sweden we can build
one houses where you can spend the
winters you you can be there 12-hour
Muncie or work pretty hard to get things
done with nature next to you okay that's
the perfect lifestyle today that would
be Canada Norway Sweden so these places
survive because they're perfectly fit
for the new digital environment but
really did it was not even about
geographical location it's about a
digital geography it's about how close
you are to the people you are networked
with to become more intelligent and
intelligence wants intelligence to fuck
intelligence and marry intelligence and
become even more intelligent meaning
cloud wants to meet another cloud and
absorb each other and become a larger
cloud if they can just manage that
[Music]
that's what we gonna see those
concentrations of intelligence so again
that means that you mister can interpret
it are gonna be the most powerful
institution for everything that means
kind of as you say the death of
marketing right it's like exactly yeah
because you've heard of market yourself
because because whoever you are will be
revealed in some sense yeah if you're
going to up say you're going to an
architecture studio in 2019 mm-hmm they
just sit and sort of move the building
slightly in one direction or the other
direction and then all the data on
Nick's which is like okay this requires
different materials you can get these
materials from here and here and in here
this one's gonna cost these are long
it's gonna take to deliver those
materials here it's just fine you spec
changing the building slightly it's
suddenly certainly got $500,000 more
expensive than you change it back
slightly and it got oh you save some
money by making it better you value the
overall cost of making the building a
certain way according to the but you're
given to make the most perfect wonderful
building
according to that other and you haven't
even used a single number because that's
what the computer does for you this is
the perfect sample already today with
synthetic intelligence the architect is
human but everything beneath the actual
artistic expression is done with the
machines we're gonna see that Gregory
feels very but part of me feels when I
hear that that that is like the
apocalypse or although the apocalypse
also means revealing or you know what's
there or I know apocalypse I don't like
it's Cataldi because this could Tala
he's the little boy is dream about the
world going under you know that's why I
record farce Kitano gist and you and I
are a collective leprechaun apocalypse
just means two drastic revolution or
change you gap to the new environment
yeah which is an evolution is absolutely
necessary
and that's exactly what digital is I'm
repeating myself Jenny this is elliptic
digital as apocalyptic yeah because so
was the printing press change everything
it certainly made Europe of all places
the center of the planet unthinkable
unfortunately yeah I'm making sort of
connections here with biblical stories
again it's like you talked about Babylon
right so yeah moving into Babylon yeah
but that's what we're heading next all
busy and follow Olli out there
interested in the true axis of our time
doesn't working with that's the grand
narrative first you you say the
narrative is possible this is how you
build it there's actually four different
ways of building it it's always been
done this how you do it it's what your
statements do second here's what's gonna
happen if you don't do it that's it is a
little bit so he says you haven't done
anything yet a large part of this stuff
in the book is going to happen no it's
not Islamist terrorists is the problem
in America it so it is almost like a
biblical revelation I'm sorry to keep
bringing up the Bible it is almost like
a biblical revelation where's the joy
and people get to go through and
everybody else gets kind of drowned in
the and the noise yeah I I don't have
the responsibility to save humanity
because I'm not the match Ark and even
the matric doesn't do that the matric
just gives you the last warning she said
and Margaret Thatcher she tells us okay
if you're not moving when I move you're
dead okay I don't have to do that that's
not my job my job is to point out we
have to go there and we can go there and
if you go there it's gonna be so much
better and then if we know before and
those who you feel the calling and are
willing to sacrifice something to join
me come on here we go and I'm not the
Moses I'm an Aaron figure meaning I'm
the priest pointing towards the chief 10
some kind of leader who can lead that's
the Exodus we're talking about the
exodus to dutiful okay a small minority
people usually people are already on the
move my biggest bet today's immigrant
women of all kinds Nigerian women who
live in Texas Ronnie and women who grew
up in Germany who live in Dubai most of
the guys I study the most right now they
are the winners women get it women are
paranoid and there's sensors on all the
time
these women have moved to these new city
states they got education they work with
real estate and fashion all kinds of
things make tons of money they got
really stubborn tough husbands about
there and don't take no for an answer
right they marry Russians they don't
they don't marry Swedish and Canadian
men he saw the real medic rats I don't
find him in Silicon Valley I think
Silicon Valley was partly creating the
foundation what's happening but yeah the
Indians of Chinese are leaving and
moving out and the guys who did the
really transformative work in Silicon
Valley are going somewhere else already
quite is where they going that's
interesting because you can create the
next huge Center for digital anywhere on
the planet if you even care about it you
can also do it all online today 100% so
it doesn't have to have a geographical
location obviously you know all
the exact quality of this webcast
between Ian in this conversation would
be little better if we've been at the
same place with one camera to share but
you can do it on zoom like we just do
and I'm a stockroom you're in Paris and
we're still best friends and we go to
London and may hang out a bit then we go
back to Paris to Stockholm we keep doing
our zooms if there's a market for it or
whatever we have an audience and we keep
getting engaged in a conversation we're
actually the physical location of our
two different bodies it's not that
interesting anymore we already did it -
there you go this is what the machines
have done to us what I like is that
about your your story here is that
you're not naively progressive and at
the same time you're not you're not
conservative or to try to tell us that
we need to get back to something you're
going both directions at the same time
you're going forward but you're also
saying we need this deep anthropology -
I talked about two new things I took one
thing from the past we have the tribe
which is still on us so it's not really
from the past mm-hmm the past is the
past
it's the no other interest and to learn
from it where we're gonna go next
completely focused on the future meaning
only what we take with us which is the
memory of our own bodies which is a
social biological evolutionary program
that worked in the original tribe and
that we still have to carry with us for
the foreseeable future
including our bodies that are not fit
for space travel sorry Ellen
it's not gonna happen so oh yeah that's
what we need to move forward
the rest is machines who I do not
particularly care about if they're alive
or not they're not alive these machines
here to service when you you you start
your ethics a lot of young guys out
there are tempted to be life centric or
biocentric or you know because they want
to be kind to cows whatever they want to
be crew or anything like that it doesn't
matter because even if your life centric
you're still anthropocentric you start
with humans right
you're a human being you're
communicating with other human beings
and no it's nobody except human beings
are gonna talk to you or listen to you
you'll be involved with your
conversation we are intraspecies within
our own species the only release on your
human being it's because of you and
myself if a big cockroach or probably
the cockroaches that was a dunker
probably be decided with the donkey's
but know you that means to try to
include other species or things like
that in your ethics and say life is more
important than being human but at the
end of the day it's gonna be like okay
so you're gonna kill a human to save a
dolphin why would we care about that
you're just being a scared little boy is
afraid of confronting the honest factual
truth the truth is that we are human and
we are talking to each other as unions
I'm not a humanist
I'm an anti-humanist like Nietzsche I I
know perfectly well a human is not a
sacred humans are not gods
we just happen to be species it happens
at least to think that it wants to live
and happens to think that it has some
kind of consciousness although that is
very available and this creature is the
creature I am and you are and we're
talking to ourselves and other humans
and then the question is this one the
planet is there for us we are not there
for the planet
we're not there to serve a certain
goddess if he called the planet the
goddess is only because it put a name on
the container because we have to find a
sustainable way for us as humans to live
on this planet if that's not about
harmony imbalance for God's sake it's
about sustainability in itself and it's
pure for meaning
we we might just as well try to avoid
climate disaster if we can we should do
our utmost to do that because we also
have to then later learn how to avoid
the next Ice Age mmm-hmm we have to turn
the planet into garden instead of wild
nature if you're gonna contain a planet
with tens or twenty or thirty billion
people on it yeah no kidding yeah yeah
which is yeah which is perfectly
feasible hmm
so to me to build the Tower of Babel
today me stay on this planet it's on the
planet we create that and if you need to
create a huge temple somewhere for
people to believe that this is the
planet we should stay on then let's do
that
but ever since 1958 we got the first
photograph of the planet from outer
space we've been really filled about
seeing ourselves from outer space
discovering this tiny planet is all we
have the rest is just cold and full of
radiation and certainly not habitable
for human beings and not meant for us at
all we must be here for a long long long
time to come
that's all that that to me is the
ultimate story of our age it's just
because the stories all this tower about
will be saucy hubris it's not grace to
you brassiere
I think the tightness out there are
always the ones who have the universe
did ask you about that like what is what
is a good utopian vision that isn't
hubristic it is echo topia that's the
name for it Neku tokyo tokyo yeah that's
the planet that's been at the current
one I'm not sure everybody's gonna be on
that planet but we probably will it make
you know space for most people to be on
the planet whether everybody would be
well I think some people will be poor or
whether people will be connected or
disconnected we don't know that yet but
all I know is that people who don't even
make an effort to be part of this planet
don't even make an effort to stand up
and move we need to move don't do the
outmost to educate themselves and to
prepare themselves for the requirement
and we put on humans to part of this way
more intelligent world than what we had
before
well those are not prepared to be part
of it and think they're just gonna be
around why would we care for them you
don't really make an effort why would I
care for people who turn themselves into
victims and don't even want to make an
effort I don't think you're NOPD's even
dares to talk about this but I do and I
think we have to